# Kiwamu Okabe - Research and Development Engineer

Phone: +81-90-3524-7064 Email: kiwamu@debian.or.jp

Homepage: http://masterq.metasepi-design.com/

## Interests

I launched my career on developing embedded devices at Ricoh Company, Ltd, and also learned application design using functional language such like Haskell. I found Metasepi project<sup>1</sup> what is trying to apply strong type to embedded programming. For my first challenging, I developed an embedded Haskell compiler named Ajhc<sup>2</sup>, and published some research papers<sup>3</sup>.

Today, I choose ATS language<sup>4</sup> as embedded functional language, and found "Japan ATS User Group<sup>5</sup>" what holds Japanese translations about the language. And I'm implementing<sup>6</sup> these technology on tiny MCU such like ARM Cortex-M series and 8bit AVR for practical use.

Metasepi is very experimental and ambitious project, however I believe that it also introduces an by-product "the technology to design real software with predictable manpower and safety" regardless of embedded domain.

# Work Experience

November 2016 - Present: Expert Engineer (permanent employee) at SELTECH CORPO-RATION

- Maintain a Hypervisor for embedded market
- Design and develop own secure OS for ARM platform

August 2014 - Present: Part-time Researcher at RIKEN Advanced Institute for Computational Science

- Research embedded functional programming running on ARM Cortex-M and AVR
- Verification for RTOS application such like ChibiOS/RT<sup>7</sup> running on ARM Cortex-M

July 2013 - Present: Self-employed Software Engineer at METASEPI DESIGN

- Research and develop Ajhc Haskell Compiler
- Host meetups<sup>8</sup> for hands-on to verify embedded application on ARM Cortex-M using STM32<sup>9</sup> board and ST-LINK<sup>10</sup> debugger

<sup>1</sup> http://www.metasepi.org/

<sup>2</sup>http://ajhc.metasepi.org/

http://www.metasepi.org/papers.html

<sup>4</sup>http://www.ats-lang.org/

<sup>5</sup>http://jats-ug.metasepi.org/

<sup>6</sup>http://fpiot.metasepi.org/

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>7</sup>http://www.chibios.org/

<sup>8</sup>https://metasepi.compass.com/

<sup>9</sup>http://www.st.com/en/microcontrollers/stm32-32-bit-arm-cortex-mcus.html

 $<sup>^{10} \</sup>mathtt{http://www.st.com/en/development-tools/st-link.html}$ 

- ATS language evangelist
- Verification evangelist using VeriFast<sup>11</sup>, which is a verifier C language programs annotated with preconditions and postconditions
- Translated VeriFast Tutorial into Japanese 12
- Support to develop any embedded software
- Manage Metasepi Project and develop the core technology

February 2016 - November 2016: Software Enginner (contract employee) at Life Robotics Inc.

- Design GUI application running on Linux OS, using C++ and Qt<sup>13</sup>
- Design network protocol for Robotics application
- Reason for Quitting: to challenge verification of secure application using C language and VeriFast

March 2015 - February 2016: System Enginner (contract employee) at Centillion Japan Co., Ltd.

- Technical support for stock chart application using JavaScript
- Maintain MySQL database servers
- Launch new IoT business for farming
- Design a platform<sup>14</sup> to accelerate R programs
- Reason for Quitting: to change my job into embedded one, again

September 2014 - December 2014: Software engineer (trustee agreement) at Axsh co., LTD.

- Develop an OpenFlow application named "OpenVNet" 15
- Design automation scripts for AWS using Ruby and GNU make
- Reason for Quitting: to have better salary

March 2012 - July 2013: Software Engineer (permanent employee) at MIRACLE LINUX CORPORATION

- $\bullet$  Maintain own Digital Signage platform running on Intel architecture using Linux OS, C++, OpenGL, GTK+  $^{16}$  and GStreamer  $^{17}$
- Verify and tune up performance of Digital Signage on new Intel platform and Intel video driver
- Verify PowerPC Linux kernel and debug/fix a race condition in the SMP kernel

<sup>11</sup>https://github.com/verifast/verifast

 $<sup>^{12} \</sup>mathtt{https://github.com/jverifast-ug/translate/blob/master/Manual/Tutorial/Tutorial.md}$ 

<sup>13</sup>https://www.qt.io/

<sup>14</sup>https://github.com/centillion-tech/kick-r

<sup>15</sup>https://github.com/axsh/openvnet

<sup>16</sup>https://www.gtk.org/

<sup>17</sup>https://gstreamer.freedesktop.org/

- Debug and fix bug of crash<sup>18</sup> command's PowerPC virtual memory paging
- Design new Windows installer using NSIS<sup>19</sup>
- Introduce and maintain new Git server for internal use
- Reason for Quitting: to focus researching and developing Ajhc Haskell compiler on full-time work

April 2001 - February 2012: Software Development Engineer (permanent employee) at Ricoh Company, Ltd.

• Reason for Quitting: to join more small and quick team

## April 2010: Port OS to new Intel hardware

I ported NetBSD-2.0<sup>20</sup> to new Intel hardware, and calculated boot time before porting the OS.

### April 2008: Develop and technical support NetBSD OS

I became technical leader to maintain and support Ricoh's multifunction printer. Also I debuged and fixed many kernel level bugs. I designed power down process by software trigger.

## April 2006: Develop POSIX thread library

I replaced old user level POSIX thread library with new NetBSD-2.0 m:n thread. My efforts are following.

- Research the presence of thread-safe and cancel-safe in kernel, libc and libpthread.
- Write test code to get thread-safe and cancel-safe.
- Add API into the m:n thread library. Because printer application depend on the missing API.
- Debug and fix signal bugs in the m:n thread library.

#### June 2004: Tune multifunction printer boot time as 10 seconds

Before my tune, the printer boot time is 30 seconds. I developed a tool analyze log dumped by bootloader, kernel, init process and application, analyze IPC network, and advice how to get speed to application developer, and split application as groups for pre-boot and post-boot. Ricoh's multifunction printer "imagio" <sup>21</sup> uses my method and tool, ever now.

#### October 2003: Develop new BIOS for multifunction printer

Develop new custom BIOS with a company at the United States.

#### November 2002: Design secure boot for multifunction printer on Intel architecture

I re-designed bootloader to support public key algorithm authentication, and designed the format include secure key in SD card

<sup>18</sup>http://people.redhat.com/~anderson/

<sup>19</sup>http://nsis.sourceforge.net/

<sup>20</sup>http://netbsd.org/

<sup>21</sup> http://www.ricoh.co.jp/imagio/

## July 2001: Develop BIOS and bootloader for multifunction printer on Intel architecture

My first work at Ricoh. Ricoh's multifunction printer "imagio" <sup>22</sup> use my bootloader design, ever now. Also I designed hardware dependent data structure to configure bootloader and kernel, and Option BIOS to boot on SD card

## Education

• March 2001: Master of Engineering from Department of Electrical and Electronic Engineering, Tokyo Metropolitan University.

The thesis: "Multimode Quartz Crystal Microbalance" 23

## Publications and Reports

- Kiwamu Okabe and Hongwei Xi. "Arduino programing of ML-style in ATS" <sup>24</sup>. ML workshop, 2015.
- Kiwamu Okabe and Takayuki Muranushi. "Systems Demonstration: Writing NetBSD Sound Drivers in Haskell" 25. Haskell Symposium, 2014.
- Kiwamu Okabe. "ATS 言語を使って不変条件を API に強制する". <sup>26</sup> 夏のプログラミング・シンポジウム 2014, 2014.
- Kiwamu Okabe, Hiroki MIZUNO and Hidekazu SEGAWA. "強い型による OS の開発手法の提案"<sup>27</sup>. 第 55 回プログラミング・シンポジウム, 2014.

## Activities

Open-source projects

## Metasepi Project<sup>28</sup>

- Challenge to create an open-source Unix-like operating system designed with strong type such as ML or Haskell.
- Rewriting NetBSD kernel using Ajhc Haskell compiler. https://github.com/metasepi/netbsd-arafura-s1

#### Aihc Haskell compiler<sup>29</sup>

- Extend and add embedded features to Jhc Haskell Compiler http://repetae.net/computer/jhc/.
- Ajhc has thread-safe and reentrant runtime. Also has Erlang style GC. It means Ajhc's Haskell context has own GC heap. GC can run on tiny CPU such as Cortex-M3 with 32kB RAM.

## Japan ATS User Group<sup>30</sup>

• An user group for ATS language promotion of utilization. Translating ATS documents into Japanese.

```
22http://www.ricoh.co.jp/imagio/
23http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110004076869
24http://www.metasepi.org/doc/metasepi-icfp2015-arduino-ats.pdf
25http://metasepi.org/doc/metasepi-icfp2014-demo.pdf
26http://www.metasepi.org/doc/20141101_prosym_summer2014.pdf
27http://metasepi.org/doc/20140110_prosym55.pdf
28http://metasepi.org/
29http://ajhc.metasepi.org/
30http://jats-ug.metasepi.org/
```

## Debian Maintainer<sup>31</sup>

• Maintained uim package at Debian squeeze, and packages using Haskell at sid.

## Carettah<sup>32</sup>

• A presentation tool written with Haskell. All of my slides<sup>33</sup> are created by the tool.

# Computer Skills

- Languages: C, C++, Haskell, ATS, Intel/ARM assembler, Ruby, JavaScript, Python
- Platforms: Linux, NetBSD, FreeRTOS, ChibiOS/RT, Android NDK, Cygwin, MinGW, Bare metal

# Reference available upon request

- Hiroyasu Fukuyama CTO SELTECH CORPORATION
- Woo-Keun Yoon CEO Life Robotics Inc.
- Kentaro Kuroiwa Research Chief Centillion Japan Co., Ltd.
- Yasuhiro Yamazaki CEO Axsh Co., Ltd.
- Takayuki Muranushi RIKEN Advanced Institute for Computational Science
- Takashi KODAMA CEO MIRACLE LINUX CORPORATION
- Shigeya SENDA Ricoh Company, Ltd.
- Hitoshi Sekimoto Professor Tokyo Metropolitan University, Department of Electrical and Electronic Engineering

Last updated: February 23, 2017

 $<sup>^{31} \</sup>verb|http://qa.debian.org/developer.php?login=kiwamu@debian.or.jp|$ 

<sup>32</sup>https://github.com/master-q/carettah

<sup>33</sup>http://www.slideshare.net/master\_q/